<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<section xml:id="section-ITLT">
    <title>Intro to Linear Transformations</title>

    <introduction>
        Another benefit of the matrix form <m>A\vec{x} = \vec{b}</m> of a linear system is that it allows us to view a matrix <m>A</m> as an object that <q>acts</q> on a vector <m>\vec{x}</m> to produce a new vector <m>A\vec{x}</m>. This is analogous to how a function <m>f(x)</m> <q>acts</q> on the number <m>x</m> to produce the output <m>f(x)</m>. This new perspective on a matrix is called a <em>transformation</em>, and it is a generalization of a real-valued function <m>f(x)</m>, developed in pre-calculus. A real-valued function has a single real number input and a single real number output. A transformation has an <m>n</m> real number inputs (a vector in <m>\mathbb{R}^n</m>), and an <m>m</m> real number output (a vector in <m>\mathbb{R}^m</m>).
    </introduction>

    <subsection>
        <title>Transformations</title>

        <definition>
            A <term>transformation</term> (or <term>mapping</term>) <m>T</m> form <m>\mathbb{R}^n</m> to <m>\mathbb{R}^m</m> is a rule which assigns to each vector <m>\vec{x} \in \mathbb{R}^n</m> a vector <m>T(\vec{x})</m> in <m>\mathbb{R}^m</m>.
            <ul>
                <li>The set <m>\mathbb{R}^n</m> is called the domain of <m>T</m> (more generally, a subset of <m>\mathbb{R}^n</m>, denoted by <m>D(T)</m>), and <m>\mathbb{R}^m</m> is called the <term>codomain</term> of <m>T</m></li>
                <li>For <m>\vec{x} \in \mathbb{R}^n</m>, the vector <m>T(\vec{x})</m> is called the <term>image</term> of <m>\vec{x}</m>.</li>
                <li>The <term>range</term> of <m>T</m> is the set of all images <m>T(\vec{x})</m>.</li>
            </ul>
        </definition>

        <p>
            The term <q>transformation</q> or <q>mapping</q> is used, however the concept is basically the same as the familiar function.
        </p>

        <p>
            Intuitively, a transformation <m>T</m> can be understood in terms of the <q>movement</q> of mapping one vector to another. More generally, <m>T</m> maps its domain <m>\mathbb{R}^n</m> to its range, and this can be thought of as moving all possible input vectors to their corresponding output vectors. In particular, in <m>\mathbb{R}^2</m> can be thought of as a transformation in the sense of geometry, a way of changing the shape of some objects in some way (translation, rotation, stretching, expansion and compression, etc.).
        </p>

        <p>
            If <m>A</m> is an <m>m \times n</m> matrix, then matrix multiplication by <m>A</m> is a transformation. In particular, the map <m>T(\vec{x}) = A\vec{x}</m> is a transformation from <m>\mathbb{R}^n</m> to <m>\mathbb{R}^m</m>.
        </p>

    </subsection>
    <subsection>
        <title>Linear Transformations</title>
        <p>
            In linear algebra, we only consider transformations with a particular <q>linear</q> property, called <q>linear transformations</q>. Recall that if <m>A</m> is an <m>m \times n</m> matrix, and <m>\vec{x}, \vec{y} \in \mathbb{R}^n</m>, then,
        </p>
        <me>
            A(\vec{x} + \vec{y}) = A\vec{x} + A\vec{y} \quad \text{and} \quad A(c\vec{x}) = cA\vec{x}
        </me>

        <p>
            These properties together make matrix multiplication a so-called <q>linear</q> transformation.
        </p>

        <definition>
            A transformation <m>T</m> is <term>linear</term> if,
            <ol>
                <li><m>T(\vec{x} + \vec{y}) = T(\vec{x}) + T(\vec{y})</m> for all <m>\vec{x}, \vec{y} \in D(T)</m>.</li>
                <li><m>T(c \vec{x}) = c T(\vec{x})</m> for all <m>c \in \mathbb{R}, \vec{x} \in D(T)</m>.</li>
            </ol>
        </definition>

        <p>
            Intuitively, property 2 means that if you scale the input by a factor of <m>c</m>, then the output will be correspondingly scaled by <m>c</m>.
        </p>

        <p>
            Linear transformations are said to be <term>operation preserving</term>, in particular preserving the operations of addition and scalar multiplication. This is because for a linear map, adding <m>\vec{x} + \vec{y}</m> in <m>\mathbb{R}^n</m> and then applying <m>T</m> is equivalent to applying <m>T</m> to <m>\vec{x}</m> and <m>\vec{y}</m> and then adding their result in <m>\mathbb{R}^m</m>.
        </p>

        <p>
            With this definition, every matrix transformation is a linear transformation. 
        </p>

        <theorem>
            <title>Maps 0 to 0</title>
            <p>
                If <m>T</m> is a linear transformation, then <m>T(\vec{0}) = \vec{0}</m>.
            </p>
        </theorem>

        <proof>
            By linearity, <m>T(\vec{0}) = T(0\vec{x}) = 0 \cdot T(\vec{x}) = \vec{0}</m>.
        </proof>

        <p>
            Geometrically, a transformation is linear if it maps all (straight) lines to lines, and fixes the origin. Linear transformations have the property that grid lines remain parallel and evenly spaced.
        </p>

        <theorem>
            <title>General linear property</title>
            <p>
                Let <m>T</m> be a linear transformation, <m>\vec{v}_1, \dots, \vec{v}_n \in D(T), a_1, \dots, a_n \in \mathbb{R}</m>. Then,
            </p>
            <me>
                \boxed{T(a_1 \vec{v}_1 + \dots + a_n \vec{v}_n) = a_1 T(\vec{v}_1) + \dots + a_n T(\vec{v}_n)}
            </me>
            <p>
                More compactly,
            </p>
            <me>
                T\brac{\sum_{k=1}^n a_k \vec{v}_k} = \sum_{k=1}^n a_k T(\vec{v}_k)
            </me>
        </theorem>
    </subsection>
</section>