<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<section xml:id="section-ITD">
    <title>Introduction to Determinants</title>
    <introduction>
        The determinant is a number associated with a matrix, which provides information about its invertibility, as well as information about its associated linear transformation. More precisely, the determinant in an operation (or function) on a matrix, i.e. whose input is a matrix, and output is a real number.
    </introduction>

    <subsection>
        <title>Determinants</title>
        <p>
            There are a few motivations for the determinant. One is as a criterion for invertibility of a matrix, which recall is equivalent to a corresponding system of equations having a unique solution. In particular, a matrix <m>A</m> is invertible if and only if the system of equations <m>A\vec{x} = \vec{b}</m> has a unique solution.
        </p>
        <p>
            First, consider the most basic case, of a <m>1 \times 1</m> matrix, of the form <m>A = \begin{bmatrix} a \end{bmatrix}</m>, which corresponds to the coefficient matrix of the single-equation system,
        </p>
        <me>
            ax = b
        </me>
        Or, in matrix form,
        <me>
            \begin{bmatrix} a \end{bmatrix} \begin{bmatrix} x \end{bmatrix} = \begin{bmatrix} b \end{bmatrix}
        </me>
        The inverse of <m>A</m> is the matrix <m>A^{-1} = \begin{bmatrix} \frac{1}{a} \end{bmatrix}</m>, provided that <m>a \neq 0</m>. Equivalently, the unique solution to the <q>system</q> is <m>x = \frac{b}{a}</m>, again provided that <m>a \neq 0</m>.
        <p>
            In general, we will define the determinant in such a way so that a matrix is invertible if and only if its determinant is non-zero. In this way, we define the determinant of a <m>1 \times 1</m> matrix as the entry itself.
        </p>

        <definition>
            <p>For a <m>1 \times 1</m> matrix <m>A = \begin{bmatrix} a \end{bmatrix}</m>, the <term>determinant</term> of <m>A</m> is <m>\det{A} = a</m>.</p>
        </definition>

        <p>
            For a <m>2 \times 2</m> matrix, of the form,
        </p>
        <me>
            A = \begin{bmatrix} a \amp b \\ c \amp d \end{bmatrix}
        </me>
        which corresponds to the system,
        <md>
            <mrow> a x_1 + b x_2 \amp = y_1 </mrow>
            <mrow> c x_1 + d x_2 \amp = y_2 </mrow>
        </md>
        Recall that the matrix <m>A</m> is invertible if and only if <m>\Delta = ad - bc \neq 0</m>. Equivalently, recall that the system has a unique solution,
        <me>
            x_1 = \frac{1}{\Delta}(d y_1 - b y_2) \qquad x_2 = \frac{1}{\Delta}(ay_2 - cy_1) 
        </me>
        provided that <m>\Delta = ad - bc \neq 0</m>. This <q>difference of the products of the diagonals</q> we will define as the determinant of a <m>2 \times 2</m> matrix.

        <definition>
            <p>For a <m>2 \times 2</m> matrix <m>A = \begin{bmatrix} a \amp b \\ c \amp d \end{bmatrix}</m>, the <term>determinant</term> of <m>A</m>, <m>\det{A}</m>, is defined by,</p>
            <me>
                \det{A} = ad - bc
            </me>
        </definition>

        <p>
            Note that we are using <q>functional notation</q> <m>\det{A}</m> for the determinant of <m>A</m>, treating <q><m>\det</m></q> as a function with argument <q><m>A</m></q>. When writing the matrix explcitly, we could write,
        </p>
        <me>
            \det{\begin{bmatrix} a \amp b \\ c \amp d \end{bmatrix}} = ad - bc
        </me>
        <p>
            Determinants are also denoted with vertical bars, as
        </p>
        <me>
            \begin{vmatrix} a \amp b \\ c \amp d \end{vmatrix} = ad - bc
        </me>
        <p>
            Intuitively, this can be thought of in some sense as a <q>magnitude</q> of the matrix, as we will see later.
        </p>
    </subsection>

    <subsection>
        <title><m>3 \times 3</m> Determinants and Larger</title>
        <p>
            For <m>3 \times 3</m> matrices and larger, evaluating determinants is more complex. Let <m>A</m> be a <m>3 \times 3</m> matrix,
        </p>
        <me>
            A = \begin{bmatrix} a_{11} \amp a_{12} \amp a_{13} \\
            a_{21} \amp a_{22} \amp a_{23} \\
            a_{31} \amp a_{32} \amp a_{33} \end{bmatrix}
        </me>
        Similarly, we want to define the determinant as a number depending on the entries of the matrix, which is equal to zero precisely when the matrix is not invertible.
    </subsection>

</section>
