<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<chapter>
    <title>Introduction to Linear Algebra</title>
    <introduction>
        <p>
            <term>Linear algebra</term> is a large branch of mathematics. It is arguably just as important and applicable as calculus, and in modern times, is arguably more applicable. From one perspective, it is the study of geometry from an algebraic perspective, and in particular only using algebra which is linear.
        </p>
        <p>
            The concepts in linear algebra are equal in importance to the computation.
        </p>
        <p>
            The pre-requisites for linear algebra are essentially just high-school algebra. That is, being comfortable with variables, equations, functions, and sets. In particular, calculus is not a necessary pre-requisite for linear algebra. However, typically linear algebra is taught at the university level, because it contains some higher levels of mathematical abstraction and mathematical reasoning.
        </p>
    </introduction>

    <subsection>
        <title>Applications of Linear Algebra</title>
        <p>
            Linear algebra has a wide range of applications. The applications of linear algebra increase over time as computing power increases. Some applications of linear algebra include:
            <ul>
                <li>
                    Applications to engineering, physics, biology, economics, and statistics.
                </li>
                <li>
                    Computer science, including computer graphics, and machine learning.
                </li>
                <li>
                    Oil exploration, ships searching for offshore oil deposits solve thousands of systems of linear equations every day. The seismic data for the equations are obtained from underwater shock waves created by explosions from air guns.
                </li>
                <li>
                    Linear programming, airlines scheduling flight crews, monitoring the location of aircraft.
                </li>
                <li>
                    Network flow (e.g. the internet, electrical networks, traffic flow, etc.), relies on linear algebra and linear systems of equations. Google's PageRank, ranking websites.
                </li>
                <li>
                    Chemistry, the geometry of molecules such as methane, balancing chemical equations as a system of equations.
                </li>
                <li>
                    Psychology, factor analysis.
                </li>
                <li>
                    pg. 1 Leontief economic analysis, ch.1.6 and 2.6, applications of linear algebra (in particular, systems of linear equations).
                </li>
                <li>
                    Robotics.
                </li>
                <li>
                    Applications to cryptography, using matrices.
                </li>
            </ul>
        </p>
        <p>
            Linear algebra also provides the foundations for other advanced topics in mathematics, including:
            <ul>
                <li>Multi-variable calculus and vector calculus.</li>
                <li>Differential equations (including partial differential equations).</li>
                <li>Abstract algebra (a generalization of linear algebra).</li>
                <li>Mathematical game theory.</li>
            </ul>
        </p>
    </subsection>

    <!-- <subsection>
        <title>Misc Notes</title>
        <ul>
            <li>
                Affine geometry is broadly, the geometry of parallels (but no notion of perpendicular).
            </li>
        </ul>
    </subsection> -->

</chapter>