<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<section xml:id="section-RRAM">
    <title>Gaussian Elimination and Matrices</title>

    <introduction>
        Then, Gaussian elimination can be reframed in terms of modifying rows of the augmented matrix of a system.
    </introduction>

    <subsection>
        <title>Elementary Row Operations</title>
        <definition>
            <title>Elementary Row Operation</title>
            <ul>
                <li><term>Interchange</term>. Interchange two rows in the matrix.</li>
                <li><term>Scaling</term>. Multiply (or divide) an equation by a non-zero real number.</li>
                <li><term>Replacement</term>. Add to one equation a multiple of another equation.</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                These row operations are denoted by,
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li><m>R_i \leftrightarrow R_j</m></li>
                <li><m>kR_i \rightarrow R_i</m></li>
                <li><m>R_i + k R_j \rightarrow R_i</m></li>
            </ul>
        </definition>

        <p>
            Performing Gaussian elimination with this matrix form removes the need of repeatedly writing the variables. This process on a matrix is also called <term>row reduction</term>.
        </p>

        <ul>
            <li>Two matrices are <term>row equivalent</term> if one can be obtained from the other by a (finite) sequence of row oeprations.</li>
            <li>A <term>zero</term> row has only zeros. A <term>non-zero</term> row is a row with at least one non-zero entry.</li>
            <li>The <term>leading entry</term> of a non-zero row is the left-most non-zero entry. It is also called the <term>leading coefficient</term>, or <term>pivot</term>.</li>
        </ul>
    </subsection>

    <subsection>
        <title>Row Echelon Form</title>

        <p>
            After Gaussian elimination is performed on a matrix, the staircase or triangular form of the matrix is called row echelon form.
        </p>

        <definition>
            A matrix is in <term>row echelon form</term> (or simply <term>echelon form</term>, or <term>REF</term>) if,
            <ol type="a">
                <li>Any zero rows are the bottom of the matrix.</li>
                <li>the leading entry of every non-zero row is always strictly to the right of any leading entry above it.</li>
            </ol>
        </definition>

        <p>
            Matrices in row echelon form have the broad form,
        </p>
        <me>
            \begin{bmatrix} a \amp \cdots \amp \cdots \amp \cdots \amp \cdots \amp \cdots \\
            0 \amp b \amp \cdots \amp \cdots \amp \cdots \amp \cdots \\
            0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp c \amp \cdots \amp \cdots \\
            0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp d \\
            0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \end{bmatrix}
        </me>
        where the pivots $a, b, c, d$ are non-zero numbers. Notice that,
        <ul>
            <li>Every entry below a pivot is 0.</li>
        </ul>

        <p>
            The terminology <i>echelon</i> is due to the step-like pattern of the non-zero entries of the matrix. The process of transforming a matrix into row echelon form is called <term>row reduction</term>. In summary,
        </p>

        <me>
            \begin{pmatrix} \text{doing operations on a} \\ \text{system of equations} \\ \text{to convert it to triangular form} \end{pmatrix} \quad \iff \quad \begin{pmatrix} \text{doing row operations on a} \\ \text{augmented matrix} \\ \text{to convert it to row echelon form} \end{pmatrix}
        </me>

        <definition>
            A <term>pivot position</term> in a matrix <m>A</m> is a location which corresponds to a leading entry in the row echelon form of <m>A</m>. A <term>pivot column</term> is a column of <m>A</m> which contains a pivot position.
        </definition>
    </subsection>

    <subsection>
        <title>Summary of Row Reduction</title>

        Consider a matrix <m>A</m>.
        <ol>
            <li>
                In the left-most non-zero column (the first pivot column), choose a non-zero entry to be the pivot, and if necessary, use a row exchange to position the pivot at the top of the column.
                <me>
                    \begin{bmatrix} a \amp \cdots \amp \cdots \amp \cdots \\
                    \vdots \amp \ddots \amp \vdots \amp \vdots \\
                    \vdots \amp \vdots \amp \vdots \amp \vdots \end{bmatrix}
                </me>
            </li>

            <li>
                Use row replacement operations to create zeros in all positions below the pivot.
                <me>
                    \begin{bmatrix} a \amp \cdots \amp \cdots \amp \cdots \\
                    0 \amp \ddots \amp \vdots \amp \vdots \\
                    0 \amp \vdots \amp \vdots \amp \vdots \end{bmatrix}
                </me>
            </li>
            <li>
                Repeat the previous steps with the remaining submatrix, ignoring the row and column of the pivot,
                <me>
                    \begin{bmatrix}
                    a \amp \cdots \amp \cdots \amp \cdots \\
                    0 \amp b \amp \vdots \amp \vdots \\
                    0 \amp 0 \amp \vdots \amp \vdots
                    \end{bmatrix}
                </me>
                Repeat this process until there are no more non-zero rows to modify.
            </li>
        </ol>
        <p>
            Finally, to convert the matrix to RREF,
        </p>
        <ol start="4">
            <li>Starting with the right-most pivot, use replacement row operations to create zeros above each pivot. If a pivot is not 1, make it 1 using a scaling operation. </li>
        </ol>
        <p>
            Steps 1-3 to convert a matrix to REF is called the <term>forward phase</term> of Gaussian elimination. Step 5 to convert it to the unique RREF is called the <term>backwards phase</term>.
        </p>
    </subsection>

    <subsection>
        <title>Remark on Gaussian Elimination</title>
        <p>
            Gaussian elimination is named after German mathematician <term>Carl Friedrich Gauss</term> (1777-1855), who developed the method in his work and helped develop the formal theory of matrices. However, similar methods of elimination were known as early as around 250-100 BC by the ancient Chinese. German engineer <term>Wilhelm Jordan</term> (1842-1899) helped popularize the method.
        </p>
    </subsection>

    <subsection>
        <title>Systems with Infinitely Many Solutions</title>
        <p>
            If the REF of the augmented matrix of a system has a zero row, then the system has infinitely many solutions.
        </p>

        <example>
            <p>
                Consider the matrix in REF,
            </p>
            <me>
                \begin{bmatrix}
                1 \amp 0 \amp -5 \amp 1 \\
                0 \amp 1 \amp 1 \amp 4 \\
                0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0
                \end{bmatrix}
            </me>
            which is the augmented matrix of the linear system,
            <md alignment="alignat">
                <mrow>x \amp \amp -5z \amp = \amp 1</mrow>
                <mrow>\amp y \amp + z \amp = \amp 4</mrow>
                <mrow>\amp \amp 0 \amp = \amp 0</mrow>
            </md>
            Notice that if we choose an arbitrary value of <m>z</m>, then we can solve for <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> in equation 1 and 2, respectively, and get a solution of the system. Here, <z>z</z> is called a <i>free variable</i>, because it can take on any value to generate a solution of the system.
        </example>
    </subsection>
    
</section>