<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<section xml:id="section-MO">
    <title>Matrix Operations</title>

    <introduction>
        Recall that an <m>m \times n</m> matrix <m>A</m> is a rectangular array of real numbers with <m>m</m> rows and <m>n</m> columns,
        <me>
            A = \begin{bmatrix}
            a_{11} \amp a_{12} \amp \dots \amp a_{1n} \\
            a_{21} \amp a_{22} \amp \dots \amp a_{2n} \\
            \vdots \amp \vdots \amp \ddots \amp \vdots \\
            a_{m1} \amp a_{n2} \amp \dots \amp a_{mn}
            \end{bmatrix}
        </me>
        The <m>j</m>th column of <m>A</m> is the column vector <m>\vec{a}_j</m>. Then, the matrix can be written as,
        <me>
            A = \begin{bmatrix} \vec{a}_1 \amp \cdots \amp \vec{a}_n \end{bmatrix}
        </me>
        The arithmetic of vectors naturally extends to the more general matrices. Recall that a vector can be thought of as a particular type of matrix.
    </introduction>

    <subsection>
        <title>Matrix Equality, Addition, Subtraction, and Scalar Multiplication</title>

        <definition>
            Two matrices <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> are <term>equal</term> if they have equal dimensions <m>m \times n</m>, and each corresponding entries are equal, i.e. <m>a_{ij} = b_{ij}</m> for all <m>i, j</m>.
        </definition>

        <definition>
            <title>Matrix addition</title>
            <p>
                Let <m>A, B</m> be <m>m \times n</m> matrices (of the same dimension). Then, the <term>sum</term> of <m>A</m> and <m>B</m>, is the matrix formed by adding the corresponding entries of <m>A</m> and <m>B</m>. In other words,
                <me>
                    \boxed{(A + B)_{ij} = \begin{bmatrix} a_{ij} + b_{ij} \end{bmatrix}}
                </me>
            </p>
        </definition>

        <p>
            Note that addition is only defined for matrices that have equal dimensions. Subtraction of matrices is defined similarly.
        </p>

        <definition>
            <title>Scalar multiplication</title>
            Let <m>A</m> be an <m>m \times n</m> matrix, <m>k \in \mathbb{R}</m> be a scalar. Then, <m>kA</m> is the matrix formed by multiplying each of the entries of <m>A</m> by <m>k</m>, or,
            <me>
                \boxed{(kA)_{ij} = kA_{ij}}
            </me>
        </definition>

        <p>
            The previous definitions focussed on the considering matrices entry-wise (that is, entry-by-entry). The operations for a matrix can also be thought of in terms of vectors.
        </p>

        <ul>
            <li>The sum <m>A + B</m> is the matrix whose columns are the sums of the corresponding columns of <m>A</m> and <m>B</m>, or,
                <me>
                    A + B = \begin{bmatrix} \vec{a}_1 + \vec{b}_1 \amp \vec{a}_2 + \vec{b}_2 \amp \cdots \amp \vec{a}_n + \vec{b}_n \end{bmatrix}
                </me></li>

            <li>The scalar multiple <m>kA</m> is the matrix whose columns are the scalar multiples of vectors <m>k \vec{a}_j</m>, or,
            <me>
                kA = \begin{bmatrix} k \vec{a}_1 \amp k \vec{a}_2 \amp \cdots \amp k \vec{a}_n \end{bmatrix}
            </me></li>
        </ul>

        <p>
            In a similar way as vectors, <m>(-1)A</m> is denoted by <m>-A</m>, and also subtraction of matrices <m>A - B</m> is just <m>A + (-1)B</m>.
        </p>
    </subsection>

    <subsection>
        <title>Properties of Matrix Addition</title>
        <definition>
            An <m>m \times n</m> matrix whose entries are all zero is called a <term>zero matrix</term>, and is typically denoted by 0.
        </definition>

        <p>
            The size of a zero matrix is usually clear from the context. The zero matrix has the property that <m>A + 0 = A</m>, i.e. it is the <term>additive identity</term> for the set of all <m>n \times m</m> matrices. Note it is clear in this equation that 0 is a matrix, since a matrix <m>A</m> cannot be added to the number 0.
        </p>

        <theorem>
            <p>
                Let <m>A, B, C</m> be <m>m \times n</m> matrices, <m>0</m> be the <m>m \times n</m> zero matrix. Then, addition has the following properties:
            </p>
            <ol>
                <li><em>Commutative property</em>.
                <me>A + B = B + A</me></li>
                <li><em>Associative property</em>.
                <me>
                    (A + B) + C = A + (B + C)
                </me></li>
                <li><em>Additive identity property</em>.
                <me>
                    A + 0 = A
                </me></li>
                <li><em>Additive inverse property</em>. For a matrix <m>A</m>, the matrix <m>-A = \begin{bmatrix} -a_{ij} \end{bmatrix}</m>, consisting of the additive inverses of the entires of <m>A</m>, is the <term>additive inverse</term> of <m>A</m>, as,
                <me>
                    A + (-A) = 0
                </me></li>
            </ol>
        </theorem>

        <p>
            The associative property means that sums of three or more matrices can be written without brackets, for example <m>A + B + C</m>.
        </p>

        <p>
            Matrix addition also follows the natural laws when combined with scalar multiplication.
        </p>

        <theorem>
            <p>
                Let <m>A, B</m> be <m>m \times n</m> matrices, <m>r, s \in \mathbb{R}</m> be scalars. Then,
            </p>
            <ol>
                <li><em>Scalar distributes over matrix addition</em>.
                <me>
                    r(A + B) = rA + rB
                </me></li>
                <li><em>Matrix distributes over scalar addition</em>.
                <me>
                    (r + s)A = rA + sA
                </me></li>
                <li><em>Associativity of scalar multiplication</em>.
                <me>
                    r(sA) = (rs)A
                </me></li>
            </ol>
        </theorem>

        <proof>
            <ul>
                <li><em>Proof of 1. for <m>2 \times 2</m> matrices</em>. Let <m>A = \begin{bmatrix} a \amp b \\ c \amp d \end{bmatrix}, B = \begin{bmatrix} e \amp f \\ g \amp h \end{bmatrix}</m>. Then,
                <md>
                    <mrow>r(A + B) = r \begin{bmatrix} a + e \amp b + f \\ c + g \amp d + h \end{bmatrix} \amp = \begin{bmatrix} r(a + e) \amp r(b + f) \\ r(c + g) \amp r(d + h) \end{bmatrix}</mrow>
                    <mrow>\amp = \begin{bmatrix} ra + re \amp rb + rf \\ rc + rg \amp rd + rh \end{bmatrix}</mrow>
                    <mrow>\amp = \begin{bmatrix} ra \amp rb \\ rc \amp rd \end{bmatrix} + \begin{bmatrix} re \amp rf \\ rg \amp rh \end{bmatrix}</mrow>
                    <mrow>\amp = r A + r B</mrow>
                </md>
                </li>
            </ul>
        </proof>
        
    </subsection>
</section>
