<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<section xml:id="section-ITD">
    <title>Introduction to Determinants</title>
    <introduction>
        The determinant is a number associated with a matrix, which provides information about its invertibility, as well as information about its associated linear transformation. More precisely, the determinant in an operation (or function) on a matrix, i.e. whose input is a matrix, and output is a real number.
    </introduction>

    <subsection>
        <title>Determinants</title>
        <p>
            There are a few motivations for the determinant. One is as a criterion for invertibility of a matrix, which recall is equivalent to a corresponding system of equations having a unique solution. In particular, a matrix <m>A</m> is invertible if and only if the system of equations <m>A\vec{x} = \vec{b}</m> has a unique solution.
        </p>
        <p>
            First, consider the most basic case, of a <m>1 \times 1</m> matrix, of the form <m>A = \begin{bmatrix} a \end{bmatrix}</m>, which corresponds to the coefficient matrix of the single-equation system,
        </p>
        <me>
            ax = b
        </me>
        Or, in matrix form,
        <me>
            \begin{bmatrix} a \end{bmatrix} \begin{bmatrix} x \end{bmatrix} = \begin{bmatrix} b \end{bmatrix}
        </me>
        The inverse of <m>A</m> is the matrix <m>A^{-1} = \begin{bmatrix} \frac{1}{a} \end{bmatrix}</m>, provided that <m>a \neq 0</m>. Equivalently, the unique solution to the <q>system</q> is <m>x = \frac{b}{a}</m>, again provided that <m>a \neq 0</m>.
        <p>
            In general, we will define the determinant in such a way so that a matrix is invertible if and only if its determinant is non-zero. In this way, we define the determinant of a <m>1 \times 1</m> matrix as the entry itself.
        </p>

        <definition>
            <p>For a <m>1 \times 1</m> matrix <m>A = \begin{bmatrix} a \end{bmatrix}</m>, the <term>determinant</term> of <m>A</m> is <m>\det{A} = a</m>.</p>
        </definition>

        <p>
            For a <m>2 \times 2</m> matrix, of the form,
        </p>
        <me>
            A = \begin{bmatrix} a \amp b \\ c \amp d \end{bmatrix}
        </me>
        which corresponds to the system,
        <md>
            <mrow> a x_1 + b x_2 \amp = y_1 </mrow>
            <mrow> c x_1 + d x_2 \amp = y_2 </mrow>
        </md>
        Recall that the matrix <m>A</m> is invertible if and only if <m>\Delta = ad - bc \neq 0</m>. Equivalently, recall that the system has a unique solution,
        <me>
            x_1 = \frac{1}{\Delta}(d y_1 - b y_2) \qquad x_2 = \frac{1}{\Delta}(ay_2 - cy_1) 
        </me>
        provided that <m>\Delta = ad - bc \neq 0</m>. This <q>difference of the products of the diagonals</q> we will define as the determinant of a <m>2 \times 2</m> matrix.

        <definition>
            <p>For a <m>2 \times 2</m> matrix <m>A = \begin{bmatrix} a \amp b \\ c \amp d \end{bmatrix}</m>, the <term>determinant</term> of <m>A</m>, <m>\det{A}</m>, is defined by,</p>
            <me>
                \det{A} = ad - bc
            </me>
        </definition>

        <p>
            Note that we are using <q>functional notation</q> <m>\det{A}</m> for the determinant of <m>A</m>, treating <q><m>\det</m></q> as a function with argument <q><m>A</m></q>. When writing the matrix explcitly, we could write,
        </p>
        <me>
            \det{\begin{bmatrix} a \amp b \\ c \amp d \end{bmatrix}} = ad - bc
        </me>
        <p>
            Determinants are also denoted with vertical bars, as
        </p>
        <me>
            \begin{vmatrix} a \amp b \\ c \amp d \end{vmatrix} = ad - bc
        </me>
        <p>
            Intuitively, this can be thought of in some sense as a <q>magnitude</q> of the matrix, as we will see later.
        </p>
    </subsection>

    <subsection>
        <title>Determinants of <m>3 \times 3</m> Matrices</title>
        <p>
            For <m>3 \times 3</m> matrices and larger, determinants become more complex. Let <m>A</m> be a <m>3 \times 3</m> matrix,
        </p>
        <me>
            A = \begin{bmatrix} a_{11} \amp a_{12} \amp a_{13} \\
            a_{21} \amp a_{22} \amp a_{23} \\
            a_{31} \amp a_{32} \amp a_{33} \end{bmatrix}
        </me>
        Similarly, we want to define the determinant as a number depending on the entries of the matrix, which is equal to zero precisely when the matrix is not invertible.

        <p>
            Suppose that <m>A</m> is invertible. Then, we want to determine what restrictions this places on the entries of <m>A</m>, through the row reduction of <m>A</m>. First, recall that <m>A</m> being invertible implies that <m>A</m> is row equivalent to <m>I</m>, and (since <m>A</m> is square) <m>A</m> has a pivot in every row and column. Then, first, there is at least one non-zero entry in the first column. Without loss of generality, assume that <m>a_{11} \neq 0</m> (otherwise, row interchange to get a pivot in the first row). Then, multiply rows 2 and 3 by <m>a_{11}</m>, and subtract suitable multiples of row 1, to get,
        </p>
        <me>
            \begin{bmatrix} a_{11} \amp a_{12} \amp a_{13} \\
            a_{11} a_{21} \amp a_{11} a_{22} \amp a_{11} a_{23} \\
            a_{11} a_{31} \amp a_{11} a_{32} \amp a_{11} a_{33} \end{bmatrix} \sim \begin{bmatrix} a_{11} \amp a_{12} \amp a_{13} \\
            0 \amp a_{11} a_{22} - a_{12} a_{21} \amp a_{11} a_{23} - a_{13} a_{21} \\
            0 \amp a_{11} a_{32} - a_{12} a_{31} \amp a_{11} a_{33} - a_{13} a_{31} \end{bmatrix}
        </me>
        <p>
            Notice that we normally would have instead done,
        </p>
        <md>
            <mrow>R_2 - \frac{a_{21}}{a_{11}} R_1 \amp \longrightarrow R_2</mrow>
            <mrow>R_3 - \frac{a_{31}}{a_{11}} R_1 \amp \longrightarrow R_3</mrow>
        </md>
        <p>
            which also obtains 0's below the first pivot. However, these row operations leads to fractional entries, which just makes the computations more complicated.
        </p>
        <p>
            Next, again since <m>A</m> has a pivot in every column, at least one of the <m>(2,2)</m>-entry or the <m>(3,2)</m>-entry is non-zero. Without loss of generality, assume that the <m>(2,2)</m>-entry is non-zero (otherwise, use a row interchange). Then, to obtain a 0 in the <m>(3,2)</m>-entry, multiply row 3 by <m>a_{11} a_{22} - a_{12} a_{21}</m>, and add <m>-(a_{11} a_{32} - a_{23} a_{31})</m> times row 2 to row 3. This results in,
        </p>
        <me>
            \begin{bmatrix} a_{11} \amp a_{12} \amp a_{13} \\
            0 \amp a_{11} a_{22} - a_{12} a_{21} \amp a_{11} a_{23} - a_{13} a_{21} \\
            0 \amp (a_{11} a_{32} - a_{12} a_{31})(a_{11} a_{22} - a_{12} a_{21}) \amp (a_{11} a_{33} - a_{13} a_{31})(a_{11} a_{22} - a_{12} a_{21}) \end{bmatrix}
        </me>
        <p>
            and finally,
        </p>
        <me>
            \begin{bmatrix} a_{11} \amp a_{12} \amp a_{13} \\
            0 \amp a_{11} a_{22} - a_{12} a_{21} \amp a_{11} a_{23} - a_{13} a_{21} \\
            0 \amp 0 \amp (a_{11} a_{33} - a_{13} a_{31})(a_{11} a_{22} - a_{12} a_{21}) - (a_{11} a_{32} - a_{12} a_{31})(a_{11} a_{23} - a_{13} a_{21}) \end{bmatrix}
        </me>
        <p>
            Then, this matrix is row equivalent to <m>I</m> only if the <m>(3,3)</m>-entry is non-zero. In other words, the following expression is non-zero,
        </p>
        <md>
            <mrow>\amp (a_{11} a_{33} - a_{12} a_{21})(a_{11} a_{22} - a_{12} a_{21}) - (a_{11} a_{22} - a_{12} a_{21})(a_{11} a_{23} - a_{12} a_{21})</mrow>
            <mrow>\amp = a_{11} \brac{a_{11} a_{22} a_{33} + a_{12} a_{23} a_{31} + a_{13} a_{21} a_{32} - a_{11} a_{23} a_{32} - a_{12} a_{21} a_{33} - a_{13} a_{22} a_{31}} \neq 0</mrow>
        </md>
        <p>
            By assumption, <m>a_{11} \neq 0</m>, so this entry is non-zero if and only if the other factor is non-zero,
        </p>
        <me>
            a_{11} a_{22} a_{33} + a_{12} a_{23} a_{31} + a_{13} a_{21} a_{32} - a_{11} a_{23} a_{32} - a_{12} a_{21} a_{33} - a_{13} a_{22} a_{31} \neq 0
        </me>
        <p>
            It turns out that the converse is also true, that if this quantity is non-zero, then the matrix <m>A</m> is invertible. For now,
        </p>

        <definition>
            <p>Let <m>A</m> be a <m>3 \times 3</m> matrix. Then, the <term>determinant</term> of <m>A</m>, <m>\det{A}</m>, is defined by,</p>
            <me>
                \boxed{\det{A} = a_{11} a_{22} a_{33} + a_{12} a_{23} a_{31} + a_{13} a_{21} a_{32} - a_{11} a_{23} a_{32} - a_{12} a_{21} a_{33} - a_{13} a_{22} a_{31}}
            </me>
        </definition>

        <p>
            This definition is notationally complex and difficult to remember, so there are multiple alternate interpretations which make hand computations easier.
        </p>
        <p>
            One pattern is that this is a combination of 6 terms, and each term is a product of 3 entries in the matrix, of one entry from each row and each column.
        </p>
    </subsection>

    <subsection>
        <title>Determinants of Larger Matrices</title>
        <p>
            In general, computing determinants is difficult.
        </p>
    </subsection>

</section>
