<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<section xml:id="section-SSOLE">
    <title>Solution Sets of Linear Equations</title>

    <subsection>
        <title>Homogeneous Systems</title>

        <definition>
            A system of linear equations is <term>homogeneous</term> if it can be written in the form <m>A\vec{x} = \vec{0}</m>, where <m>A</m> is an <m>m \times n</m> matrix and <m>\vec{0}</m> is the zero vector in <m>\mathbb{R}^m</m>. Otherwise, a system <m>A\vec{x} = \vec{b}</m> is said to be <term>non-homogeneous</term>.
        </definition>

        <p>
            Homogeneous systems always have at least one solution (that is, they are always consistent), in particular the solution <m>\vec{x} = \vec{0}</m>, often called the <term>trivial</term> solution. Then, we want to consider whether <m>A\vec{x} = \vec{0}</m> has any <term>non-trivial</term> solutions, that is, solutions <m>\vec{x}</m> which are not the zero vector.
        </p>

        <p>
            Recall that if a system is consistent, then it has a unique solution if the REF of its augmented matrix has no free variables, and it has infinitely many solution if there at least one free variable. Then, for homogeneous systems,
        </p>
        
        <theorem>
            <p>The homogeneous system <m>A\vec{x} = \vec{0}</m> has a non-trivial solution if and only if the system has at least one free variable.</p>
        </theorem>
        <p>
            The solution set of a homogeneous equation can always be written as the span of some collection of vectors. If the system has no non-trivial solutions, then the solution set is <m>\Span{\vec{0}} = \vec{0}</m>.
        </p>
    </subsection>

    <subsection>
        <title>Non-homogeneous Systems</title>
        
        <theorem>
            <p>Let <m>A\vec{x} = \vec{b}</m> be a linear system, which is consistent with solution <m>\vec{v}_p</m>. Then, the solution set of <m>A\vec{x} = \vec{b}</m> is the set of all vectors of the form <m>\vec{v} = \vec{v}_p + \vec{v}_h</m>, where <m>\vec{v}_h</m> is any solution of the associated homogeneous system.</p>
        </theorem>
        <proof>
            <p>
                If <m>\vec{v}_p</m> is a solution of <m>A\vec{x} = \vec{b}</m>, and <m>\vec{v}_h</m> is a solution of the associated homogeneous system, then <m>A\vec{v}_p = \vec{b}</m> and <m>A\vec{v}_h = \vec{0}</m>. Then,
            </p>
            <md>
                <mrow>A(\vec{v}_p + \vec{v}_h) \amp = \underbrace{A\vec{v}_p}_{=\vec{b}} + \underbrace{A\vec{v}_h}_{=\vec{0}}</mrow>
                <mrow>\amp = \vec{b} + \vec{0}</mrow>
                <mrow>\amp = \vec{b}</mrow>
            </md>
        </proof>
    </subsection>

    <subsection>
        <title>Solving a Consistent System in Parametric Vector Form</title>
        <ol>
            <li>Use row reduction to convert the augmented matrix to RREF.</li>
            <li>Solve for each basic variable in terms of any free variables.</li>
            <li>Write a typical solution <m>\vec{x}</m> as a vector which depends on any free variables</li>
            <li>Decompose <m>\vec{x}</m> into a linear combination of vectors with only numerical entries, and use free variables as parameters.</li>
        </ol>
    </subsection>
</section>